# Roberto S. Silva Filho

home: San Francisco Bay Area, Dublin, CA, USA mobile: (949) 885-6821

e-mail: Roberto.SilvaFilho@gmail.com http://www.ics.uci.edu/~rsilvafi

#### **EXPERTISE**

Experienced researcher and practitioner in the areas of software engineering automation and collaborative applications. Development of Web, mobile and wearable apps to optimize industrial work. Research contributions to: automated and collaborative software engineering, software architecture, model-driven systems development & testing, event-driven middleware, workflow management systems and groupware. Production of patents & research papers.

## WORK EXPERIENCE

2013 - present. GE Global Research, San Ramon, CA

Lead Scientist, Human Systems Interaction Lab.

Full stack R&D of industrial intelligent software systems. Applying UX, IoT, AI services & Software Engineering techniques to automate and optimize their workflow.

Keywords: Web, mobile & wearable industrial apps, distributed simulation platforms and UX.

#### 2009 - 2013. SIEMENS Corporate Technology, Princeton, NJ

**Software Engineer/Researcher**, Software Architecture Development Lab.

Research and development of advanced software engineering tools & methods for the automation and optimization of industrial systems across SIEMENS businesses.

*Keywords*: Software Architecture Analysis and Improvement, Software Quality Assurance, Model-Driven Development & Testing, Workflow Automation.

## Summer 2004. IBM T. J. Watson Research Center, Cambridge, MA

**Research Intern**, Collaborative User Experience Lab.

Developed, benchmarked and compared different architectural approaches for the construction of contextual collaboration servers used within IBM products.

Keywords: Contextual collaboration servers, performance simulation and benchmarking.

## 2000 – 2009. University of California, Irvine, CA

(2002-2009): Graduate Research Assistant

(2000-2002): Teaching Assistant

## **EDUCATION**

2009. **Ph.D. Information and Computer Sciences**. UC, Irvine, CA, USA. GPA: 3.974/4.0

Concentration areas: Empirical Software Engineering, Event-Based Middleware, CSCW Dissertation Title: An Empirical Study of Publish/Subscribe Middleware Versatility

2003. **M.Sc. Information and Computer Sciences.** UC, Irvine, CA, USA. GPA: 3.906/4.0 *Concentration area*: **Software Engineering** 

2000. **M.Sc. Computer Science**. University of Campinas (UNICAMP), Brazil, GPA: 3.857/4.0 *Thesis Title*: Distributed Software Architectures for Large-scale Workflow using CORBA

1998. B.Sc. Computer Engineering. University of Campinas (UNICAMP), Brazil, GPA: 0.748/1.0

## **SELECTED PROJECTS**

2014 - present. GE Global Research.

- **Digital Ghost App.** Developed Web app to visualize cyber-attacks on industrial assets. Built the infrastructure to log and analyze high-throughput time series data produced by the Digital Ghost agents, allowing users to rapidly detect and respond do cyber threats detected on critical industrial infrastructure.
- Distributed Platform for Rapid Simulation Prototyping. Design & implementation of messagedriven framework supporting micro-services that facilitate the development of next generation train handling and controls. Implemented Web and mobile apps using the new framework.
- **Machining Cost Optimization**. Developed Web app that optimizes CNC machining operations, allowing aviation workshop workers to save costs, and share their expertise throughout the organization.

- **Fieldwork Automation**: Develop Mobile app used by GE Power field engineers. The app is as a single point of access to all their information needs including: project management, time keeping, schematics & documents, reporting, and collaboration. Implemented server-side API gateway and offline operation.
- **Model-based robotic inspection**. Implemented middleware connecting UI and controls, allowing supervised semi-autonomous robotic inspections of industrial assets.
- **Wearables@GE**. Applied speech recognition and wearable computing in support of hands-free workflows including: wireless measurements, photo documentation, real-time video communication.
- 2009 2013. SIEMENS Corporate Research.

**IDE for model-based test automation**: Project manager & developer for TEDESO/UML, a model-based testing IDE. Lead, for 4 years, a small team of interns in the development of extensions and core capabilities including requirements-driven regression and prioritization of tests and workflow-driven UI. TEDESO can achieve high degrees of test coverage, by automatically generating tests based on UML system specification, at a fraction of time of conventional manual testing approaches. *Technologies:* Java, Eclipse RCP, GEF, UML, model-based testing, Jenkins, Cruise Control.

2007 – 2009. UC, Irvine (UCI). **Analysis of Flexibility Trade-offs in Publish/Subscribe Infrastructures**: Developed YANCEES, a versatile pub/sub middleware evaluating it against different research and industrial message-oriented middleware, measuring and comparing their performance, maintainability, reusability, usability and flexibility. Produced different versatile software design principles and best practices.

Technologies: Java, CORBA-NS, JMS, JavaSpaces, Siena, YANCEES, OO metrics and analysis.

1998 – 2000. University of Campinas, São Paulo, Brazil (UNICAMP): **Agent-based Workflow on Distributed Environment**: Developed and evaluated the scalability of a distributed architecture for large-scale workflow as part of my Master's Thesis. This work shows the scalability benefits of a peer-to-peer agent-based workflow management system and discusses extra security and management costs induced by the approach.

Technologies: Java, JavaCC, CORBA, Workflow Management Systems, Mobile Agents, benchmarking.

## TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Fall 2001 – Spring 2002. Introduction to Computer Science II. UC, Irvine (UCI)

Topics: Data Structures, Software Complexity, Java and Scheme programming.

Fall. 2000. Introduction to Software Engineering. UC, Irvine (UCI)

Topics: Software Engineering fundamental principles, techniques and processes.

## HONORS AND AWARDS

2007. Bren School Summer Dissertation Fellowship, UC, Irvine, CA.

2001. Best thesis award (second place): VIII CLEI-UNESCO Latin American M.Sc. Thesis Context.

1998 – 2000. Scholarships to support M.Sc. Studies from FAPESP and CNPq, Brazil Research Agencies.

## **SKILLS**

**Programming Languages**: Java, JavaScript, SQL, C#, Python, Go, LISP, Pascal, Prolog, C, C++, others. **Technologies**: UI frameworks: Polymer, Vue.js, React, AngularJS; Mobile computing: Android, Cordova; Distributed Systems: REST Web Services, Docker, Event-based middleware, Distributed Network Objects (RMI, CORBA); Software Engineering: Software Product Line Engineering, UML Modeling, Software Architecture and ADLs, Aspect-Oriented Programming, Eclipse RCP and OSGi.

**Processes**: Agile Methods and Object-Oriented design principles and metrics, Rational Unified Process. **Operating Systems**: Unix/Linux and Windows administration.

## **PATENTS & PUBLICATIONS**

Author of more than 35 peer-reviewed publications; 6 US patents and 12 technical reports. More details at the website: <a href="https://rsilvafi.github.io/publications.html">https://rsilvafi.github.io/publications.html</a>